Elder Dieter F. Uchtdorf
Missionary Work: Sharing What Is in Your Heart

Last month the Twelve were invited by our dear prophet, President Russell M. Nelson, to travel with him to the dedication of the Rome Italy Temple. While traveling, I thought about the Apostle Paul and his journeys. In his day, to get from Jerusalem to Rome, it would have taken about 40 days. Today, in one of my favorite airplanes, it takes less than 3 hours.

Bible scholars believe that Paul was in Rome when he wrote several of his letters, which were key in strengthening Church members then as well as today.

Paul and the other members of the ancient Church, the Early-day Saints, were intimately familiar with sacrifice. Many were severely persecuted, even unto death.

In the last 200 years, the members of the restored Church of Jesus Christ, the Latter-day Saints, have also experienced persecution in many forms. But in spite of that persecution (and sometimes because of it), The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints has continued to grow and is now found all across the globe.

However, before we bake a cake, throw confetti, and congratulate ourselves on this remarkable success, we would do well to put that growth into perspective.

There are roughly seven and a half billion people in the world, compared to some 16 million members of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints—a very small flock indeed.[1]

Meanwhile, the numbers of Christian believers in some parts of the world are shrinking.[2]

Even in the Lord’s restored Church—while overall membership continues to grow—there are too many who do not claim the blessings of regular Church participation.

In other words, wherever you are on this earth, there are plenty of opportunities to share the good news[3] of the gospel of Jesus Christ with people you meet, study with, and live with or work and socialize with.

During this past year, I have had the exciting opportunity to be deeply involved with the worldwide missionary activities of the Church. I have often pondered and prayed about the Savior’s great commission to His disciples—us, His children—to “go ye therefore, and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost.”[4]

I wrestled with the question “How can we, as members and disciples of Christ, best fulfill that great commission in our daily lives?”

Today I invite you to ponder that same question in your heart and mind.[5]

Church leaders have emphasized the clarion call “Every member a missionary!” for decades.[6]

Members of the Church of Jesus Christ—both in past times as well as in ours—have enthusiastically and joyfully shared the gospel with friends and acquaintances. Their hearts are aflame with the testimony of Jesus Christ, and they sincerely want others to experience the same joy they have found in the Savior’s gospel.

Some members of the Church seem to have a gift for this. They love being ambassadors of the gospel. They boldly and gladly serve and lead the work as member missionaries.

However, others of us are more hesitant. When missionary work is discussed in Church meetings, heads are slowly lowered until submerged behind the pew, eyes focused on the scriptures or closed in deep meditation to avoid eye contact with other members.

Why is this? Maybe we feel guilty for not doing more to share the gospel. Perhaps we feel uncertain about how to do it. Or we might feel timid about going outside our comfort zone.

I understand this.

But remember, the Lord has never required expert, flawless missionary efforts. Instead, “the Lord requireth the heart and a willing mind.”[7]

If you are already happily doing missionary work, please continue, and stand as an example to others. The Lord will bless you.

If, however, you feel that you have been dragging your feet when it comes to sharing the gospel message, may I suggest five guilt-free things anyone can do to participate in the Savior’s great commission to help gather Israel?

First, draw close to God. The first great commandment is to love God.[8] It is a primary reason why we are on this earth. Ask yourself, “Do I really believe in Heavenly Father?”

“Do I love and trust Him?”

The closer you draw to our Heavenly Father, the more His light and joy will shine from within you. Others will notice that there is something unique and special about you. And they will ask about it.

Second, fill your heart with love for others. This is the second great commandment.[9] Try to truly see everyone around you as a child of God. Minister to them—regardless of whether their names appear on your ministering sister or brother list.

Laugh with them. Rejoice with them. Weep with them. Respect them. Heal, lift, and strengthen them.

Strive to emulate the love of Christ and have compassion for others—even to those who are unkind to you, who mock you and wish to cause you harm. Love them and treat them as fellow children of Heavenly Father.

Third, strive to walk the path of discipleship. As your love for God and His children deepens, so does your commitment to follow Jesus Christ.

You learn about His way by feasting upon His word and heeding and applying the teachings of modern prophets and apostles. You grow in confidence and courage to follow His way as you communicate with Heavenly Father with a teachable, humble heart.

Walking the path of discipleship takes practice—each day, little by little, “grace for grace,”[10] “line upon line.”[11] Sometimes two steps forward and one step back.

The important thing is that you don’t give up; keep trying to get it right. You will eventually become better, happier, and more authentic. Talking with others about your faith will become normal and natural. In fact, the gospel will be such an essential, precious part of your lives that it would feel unnatural not to talk about it with others. That may not happen immediately—it is a lifelong effort. But it will happen.

Fourth, share what is in your heart. I am not asking that you stand on a street corner with a megaphone and shout out Book of Mormon verses. What I am asking is that you always look for opportunities to bring up your faith in natural and normal ways with people—both in person as well as online. I am asking that you “stand as witnesses”[12] of the power of the gospel at all times—and when necessary, use words.[13]

Because “the gospel of Christ … is the power of God unto salvation,” you can be confident, courageous, and humble as you share it.[14] Confidence, courage, and humility may seem like contradictory attributes, but they are not. They reflect the Savior’s invitation not to hide gospel values and principles under a bushel but to let your light shine, that your good works may glorify your Father in Heaven.[15]

There are many normal and natural ways to do this, from daily acts of kindness to personal testimonials on YouTube, Facebook, Instagram, or Twitter to simple conversations with people you meet. This year we are learning from the New Testament in our homes and in Sunday School. What a marvelous opportunity to invite friends and neighbors to church and your homes to learn about the Savior with you. Share with them the Gospel Library app, where they can find Come, Follow Me. If you know young people and their families, give them the For the Strength of Youth booklet and invite them to come and see how our young people strive to live by those principles.

If someone asks about your weekend, don’t hesitate to talk about what you experienced at church. Tell about the little children who stood in front of a congregation and sang with eagerness how they are trying to be like Jesus. Talk about the group of youth who spent time helping the elderly in rest homes to compile personal histories. Talk about the recent change in our Sunday meeting schedule and how it blesses your family. Or explain why we emphasize that this is the Church of Jesus Christ and that we are Latter-day Saints, just as the members of the ancient Church were also called Saints.

In whatever ways seem natural and normal to you, share with people why Jesus Christ and His Church are important to you. Invite them to “come and see.”[16] Then encourage them to come and help. There are numerous opportunities for people to help in our Church.

Pray not only for the missionaries to find the elect. Pray daily with all your heart that you will find those who will come and see, come and help, and come and stay. Keep the full-time missionaries in the loop. They are like angels, ready to help!

As you share the good news, the gospel of Jesus Christ, do so with love and patience. If we interact with people with the sole expectation that they soon will don a white jumpsuit and ask for directions to the nearest baptismal font, we’re doing it wrong.

Some who come and see will, perhaps, never join the Church; some will at a later time. That is their choice. But that doesn’t change our love for them. And it doesn’t change our enthusiastic efforts to continue inviting individuals and families to come and see, come and help, and come and stay.

Fifth, trust the Lord to work His miracles. Understand that it’s not your job to convert people. That is the role of the Holy Ghost. Your role is to share what is in your heart and live consistent with your beliefs.

So, don’t be discouraged if someone does not accept the gospel message immediately. It is not a personal failure.

That is between the individual and Heavenly Father.

Yours is to love God and love your neighbors, His children.

Believe, love, do.

Follow this path, and God will work miracles through you to bless His precious children.

These five suggestions will help you to do what disciples of Jesus Christ have done since ancient times. His gospel and His Church are an important part of your life and of who you are and what you do. Therefore, invite others to come and see and come and help, and God will do His saving work, and they will come and stay.

“But,” you might ask, “what if I do all this and people react poorly? What if they are critical about the Church? What if they unfriend me?”

Yes, that may happen. Since ancient times, disciples of Jesus Christ have often been persecuted.[17] The Apostle Peter said, “Rejoice … as you share Christ’s sufferings.”[18] The early Saints rejoiced “that they were counted worthy to suffer shame for his name.”[19]

Remember, the Lord works in mysterious ways. It may be that by your Christlike response to rejection a hardened heart could be softened.

As an Apostle of the Lord Jesus Christ, I bless you with the confidence to be a living testimonial of gospel values, with the courage to always be recognized as a member of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, with the humility to assist in His work as an expression of your love for Heavenly Father and His children.

My dear friends, you will rejoice in knowing that you are a significant part in the long-foretold gathering of Israel, preparing for Christ’s coming in “power and great glory; with all the holy angels.”[20]

Heavenly Father knows you. The Lord loves you. God will bless you. This work is ordained of Him. You can do this. We can all do this together.

I so testify in the name of Jesus Christ, amen.

The great prophet Nephi saw in vision that even though the Church of the Lamb of God would spread “upon all the face of the earth,” because of wickedness in the world its overall “numbers [would be] few” (1 Nephi 14:12; see also Luke 12:32). ↩

For example, a recent study by the Pew Research Center found that in the United States, “the percentage of adults (ages 18 and older) who describe themselves as Christians has dropped by nearly eight percentage points in just seven years, from 78.4% in … 2007 to 70.6% in 2014. Over the same period, the percentage of Americans who are religiously unaffiliated—describing themselves as atheist, agnostic or ‘nothing in particular’—has jumped more than six points, from 16.1% to 22.8%” (“America’s Changing Religious Landscape,” Pew Research Center, May 12, 2015, pewforum.org). ↩

The word gospel means “good news.” The good news is that Jesus Christ has made a perfect Atonement that will redeem all mankind from the grave and reward each individual according to his or her works. This Atonement began with His appointment in the premortal world, continued during His mortal sojourn, and culminated with His glorious Resurrection. The biblical records of His mortal life, ministry, and sacrifice are called the Gospels: Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John. ↩

Matthew 28:19. ↩

“Verily I say unto you, my friends, I leave these sayings with you to ponder in your hearts” (Doctrine and Covenants 88:62).  ↩

President David O. McKay encouraged “every member [to be] a missionary” when he presided over the European Mission from 1922 to 1924, and he shared that same message with the Church in general conference as early as 1952 (see “‘Every Member a Missionary’ Motto Stands Firm Today,” Church News, Feb. 20, 2015, news.ChurchofJesusChrist.org). ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 64:34. ↩

See Matthew 22:37–38. ↩

See Matthew 22:39. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 93:12. ↩

Isaiah 28:10. ↩

Mosiah 18:9. ↩

This thought is often attributed to Saint Francis of Assisi; see also John 10:36–38. ↩

Romans 1:16. ↩

See Matthew 5:15–16. ↩

John 1:46; emphasis added. ↩

See John 15:18. ↩

1 Peter 4:13, English Standard Version; see also verses 1–19 for more about how followers of Christ should view suffering for the gospel’s sake. ↩

Acts 5:41. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 45:44. ↩

Elder Dale G. Renlund
Abound with Blessings

My dear brothers and sisters, our Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ desire to bless each of us.[1] The question of how to access and obtain those blessings has been the subject of theological debate and discussion for centuries.[2] Some contend that blessings are completely earned; we receive them only through our works. Others argue that God has already chosen who He will bless and how—and that these determinations are unchangeable. Both positions are fundamentally flawed. Blessings from heaven are neither earned by frenetically accruing “good deed coupons” nor by helplessly waiting to see if we win the blessing lottery. No, the truth is much more nuanced but more appropriate for the relationship between a loving Heavenly Father and His potential heirs—us. Restored truth reveals that blessings are never earned, but faith-inspired actions on our part, both initial and ongoing, are essential.[3]

As we consider how we receive blessings from God, let us liken heavenly blessings to a massive pile of wood. Imagine at the center a small mound of kindling, topped by a layer of wood chips. Sticks come next, then small logs, and finally huge logs. This woodpile contains an enormous amount of fuel, capable of producing light and heat for days. Envision next to the woodpile a single match, the kind with a phosphorus tip.[4]

For the energy in the woodpile to be released, the match needs to be struck and the kindling lit. The kindling will quickly catch fire and cause the larger pieces of wood to burn. Once this combustion reaction starts, it continues until all the wood is burned or the fire is deprived of oxygen.

Striking the match and lighting the kindling are small actions that enable the potential energy of the wood to be released.[5] Until the match is struck, nothing happens, regardless of the size of the woodpile. If the match is struck but not applied to the kindling, the amount of light and heat released from the match alone is miniscule and the combustion energy in the wood remains unreleased. If oxygen is not supplied at any point, the combustion reaction stops.

In a similar way, most blessings that God desires to give us require action on our part—action based on our faith in Jesus Christ. Faith in the Savior is a principle of action and of power.[6] First we act in faith; then the power comes—according to God’s will and timing. The sequence is crucial.[7] The required action, though, is always tiny when compared to the blessings we ultimately receive.[8]

Consider what happened when fiery, flying serpents came among the ancient Israelites on their way to the promised land. The bite of a poisonous serpent was fatal. But a bitten individual could be healed by looking at a brass serpent fashioned by Moses and placed on a pole.[9] How much energy does it take to look at something? All who looked accessed the powers of heaven and were healed. Other Israelites who were bitten failed to look at the brazen serpent and died. Perhaps they lacked the faith to look.[10] Perhaps they did not believe that such a simple action could trigger the promised healing. Or perhaps they willfully hardened their hearts and rejected the counsel of God’s prophet.[11]

The principle of activating blessings that flow from God is eternal. Like those ancient Israelites, we too must act on our faith in Jesus Christ to be blessed. God has revealed that “there is a law, irrevocably decreed in heaven before the foundations of this world, upon which all blessings are predicated—and when we obtain any blessing from God, it is by obedience to that law upon which it is predicated.”[12] That being said, you do not earn a blessing—that notion is false—but you do have to qualify for it. Our salvation comes only through the merits and grace of Jesus Christ.[13] The immensity of His atoning sacrifice means that the woodpile is infinite; our puny actions approach zero in comparison. But they are not zero, and they are not insignificant; in the dark, a match that is lit can be seen for miles. In fact, it can be seen in heaven because small acts of faith are required to ignite God’s promises.[14]

To receive a desired blessing from God, act with faith, striking the metaphorical match on which the heavenly blessing is contingent. For example, one of the objects of prayer is to secure blessings that God is willing to grant but that are made conditional on our asking.[15] Alma cried out for mercy, and his pains resolved; he was no longer harrowed up by the memory of his sins. His joy overwhelmed his pain—all because he cried out with faith in Jesus Christ.[16] The activation energy needed for us is to have enough faith in Christ to sincerely ask God in prayer and accept His will and timing for the answer.

Often, the activation energy needed for blessings requires more than just looking or asking; ongoing, repeated, faith-filled actions are required. In the middle of the 19th century, Brigham Young directed a group of Latter-day Saints to explore and settle Arizona, an arid region in North America. After reaching Arizona, the group ran out of water and feared they would perish. They pled with God for help. Soon rain and snow fell, allowing them to fill their barrels with water and provide for their livestock. Grateful and refreshed, they returned to Salt Lake City rejoicing in the goodness of God. Upon their return, they reported the details of their expedition to Brigham Young and pronounced their conclusion that Arizona was uninhabitable.

After listening to the report, Brigham Young asked a man in the room what he thought about the expedition and the miracle. That man, Daniel W. Jones, tersely replied, “I would have filled up, went on, and prayed again.” Brother Brigham put his hand on Brother Jones and said, “This is the man that shall take charge of the next trip to Arizona.”[17]

We can all recall times when we have pushed on and prayed again—and blessings resulted. The experiences of Michael and Marian Holmes illustrate these principles. Michael and I served together as Area Seventies. I was always thrilled whenever he was called on to pray in our meetings because his deep spirituality was readily apparent; he knew how to speak with God. I loved to hear him pray. Early in their marriage, though, Michael and Marian were not praying or attending church. They were busy with three little children and a successful construction company. Michael did not feel that he was a religious man. One evening, their bishop came to their home and encouraged them to begin praying.

After the bishop left, Michael and Marian decided that they would try to pray. Before going to bed, they knelt at their bedside and, uncomfortably, Michael began. After a few awkward words of prayer, Michael abruptly stopped, saying, “Marian, I can’t do this.” As he stood and began walking away, Marian grabbed him by the hand, dragged him back to his knees, and said, “Mike, you can do this. Try again!” With this encouragement, Michael finished a short prayer.

The Holmeses began to pray regularly. They accepted a neighbor’s invitation to attend church. As they walked into the chapel and heard the opening hymn, the Spirit whispered to them, “This is true.” Later, unseen and unasked, Michael helped haul some trash from the meetinghouse. As he did, he felt a distinct impression, “This is My house.”

Michael and Marian accepted Church callings and served in their ward and stake. They were sealed to each other, and their 3 children were sealed to them. More children followed, bringing the total to 12. The Holmeses served as mission president and companion—twice.

The first clunky prayer was a small but faith-filled action that triggered the blessings of heaven. The Holmeses fed the flames of faith by attending church and serving. Their dedicated discipleship over the years has led to a raging inferno that inspires to this day.

A fire, however, must receive a constant supply of oxygen for the wood to ultimately release its full potential. As demonstrated by Michael and Marian Holmes, faith in Christ requires ongoing action for the blaze to continue. Small actions fuel our ability to walk along the covenant path and lead to the greatest blessings God can offer. But oxygen flows only if we figuratively keep moving our feet. Sometimes we need to make a bow and arrow before revelation comes as to where we should search for food.[18] Sometimes we need to make tools before revelations come as to how to build a ship.[19] Sometimes, at the direction of the Lord’s prophet, we need to bake a small cake from the little oil and flour we have to receive an unfailing cruse of oil and barrel of flour.[20] And sometimes we need to “be still and know that [God is] God” and trust in His timing.[21]

When you receive any blessing from God, you can conclude that you have complied with an eternal law governing reception of that blessing.[22] But remember that the “irrevocably decreed” law is time insensitive, meaning blessings come on God’s timetable. Even ancient prophets in search of their heavenly home[23] “died in faith, not having received the promises, but having seen them afar off … [and] were persuaded … and embraced them.”[24] If a desired blessing from God has not been received—yet—you do not need to go crazy, wondering what more you need to do. Instead, heed Joseph Smith’s counsel to “cheerfully do all things that lie in [your] power; and then … stand still, with the utmost assurance, to see the … arm [of God] … revealed.”[25] Some blessings are reserved for later, even for the most valiant of God’s children.[26]

Six months ago a home-centered, Church-supported plan to learn doctrine, strengthen faith, and fortify individuals and families was introduced. President Russell M. Nelson promised that the changes can help us survive spiritually, increase our gospel joy, and deepen our conversion to Heavenly Father and Jesus Christ.[27] But it is up to us to claim these blessings. We are each responsible to open and study Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families, along with the scriptures and other Come, Follow Me material.[28] We need to discuss them with our family and friends and organize our Sabbath day to light a metaphorical fire. Or we can leave the resources sitting in a pile in our homes with the potential energy trapped inside.

I invite you to faithfully activate heavenly power to receive specific blessings from God. Exercise the faith to strike the match and light the fire. Supply the needed oxygen while you patiently wait on the Lord. With these invitations, I pray that the Holy Ghost will guide and direct you so that you, like the faithful person described in Proverbs, will “abound with blessings.”[29] I testify that your Heavenly Father and His Beloved Son, Jesus Christ, live, are concerned with your welfare, and delight to bless you, in the name of Jesus Christ, amen.

See Doctrine and Covenants 41:1; 78:17; 104:33. ↩

See, for instance, Craig Harline, A World Ablaze: The Rise of Martin Luther and the Birth of the Reformation (2017), 20. One such debate was between Augustine (AD 354–430) and his rival Pelagius (AD 354–420). Pelagius maintained that “humans certainly [had] it inside them to do good, and that they earned God’s grace by acting on that goodness and keeping all of God’s commandments.” Augustine vehemently disagreed. See also Eric Metaxas, Martin Luther: The Man Who Rediscovered God and Changed the World (2017), 296. Luther taught that works could never lead to God’s grace; faith leads to grace and good works follow; “it is impossible to separate works from faith, quite as impossible as to separate heat and light from fire.” ↩

See Doctrine and Covenants 82:10. ↩

This is a camping match, a “strike anywhere” match. Modern safety matches, like kitchen matches, have the phosphorous on the strike strip rather than on the match tip. ↩

These actions constitute the “activation energy” for the blaze. The term “activation energy” was introduced in 1889 by the Swedish scientist Svante Arrhenius. ↩

See Lectures on Faith (1985), 3. ↩

See David A. Bednar, “Ask in Faith,” Ensign or Liahona, May 2008, 94. ↩

See Mosiah 2:24–25. ↩

See Numbers 21:6–9. ↩

See 1 Nephi 17:41. ↩

See 1 Nephi 17:42. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 130:20–21. ↩

See 2 Nephi 10:24; 25:23. ↩

See Alma 60:11, 21; Dallin H. Oaks, “Small and Simple Things,” Ensign or Liahona, May 2018, 89–92; M. Russell Ballard, “Be Anxiously Engaged,” Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2012, 29–31. ↩

See Bible Dictionary, “Prayer”; see also Moroni 7:48. ↩

See Alma 36:18–21; see also Enos 1:5–8. ↩

Daniel W. Jones, 40 Years Among the Indians (1960), 222. ↩

See 1 Nephi 16:23. ↩

See 1 Nephi 17:9. ↩

See 1 Kings 17:10–16. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 101:16. ↩

See Doctrine and Covenants 130:20–21. ↩

See Hebrews 11:16. ↩

Hebrews 11:13. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 123:17. ↩

See Jeffrey R. Holland, “An High Priest of Good Things to Come,” Ensign, Nov. 1999, 36–38; Liahona, Jan. 2000, 42–45. Elder Holland said, “Some blessings come soon, some come late, and some don’t come until heaven; but for those who embrace the gospel of Jesus Christ, they come.” ↩

See Russell M. Nelson, “Opening Remarks,” Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 6–8. ↩

See Quentin L. Cook, “Deep and Lasting Conversion to Heavenly Father and the Lord Jesus Christ,” Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 8–12. ↩

Proverbs 28:20. ↩

Elder Quentin L. Cook
Great Love for Our Father’s Children

My dear brothers and sisters, this is a unique and pivotal time in history. We are blessed to live in the last dispensation before the Second Coming of the Savior. Near the commencement of this dispensation, in 1829, the year before the Church was formally organized, a beloved revelation was received, declaring that “a marvelous work” was “about to come forth.” This revelation established that those who desired to serve God qualify for such service through “faith, hope, charity and love, with an eye single to the glory of God.”[1] Charity, which is “the pure love of Christ,”[2] includes God’s eternal love for all His children.[3]

My purpose this morning is to emphasize the essential role of that kind of love in missionary work, temple and family history work, and home-centered, Church-supported family religious observance. Love of the Savior and love of our fellow men and women[4] is the primary attribute and motive for ministering and the spiritual purposes[5] we were charged to undertake by our beloved prophet, President Russell M. Nelson, in the adjustments announced in 2018.

I was exposed to the relationship between missionary work and love early in my life. When I was 11 years old, I received a patriarchal blessing from a patriarch who was also my grandfather.[6] That blessing said in part, “I bless you with great love for your fellowmen, for thou shalt be called to carry the gospel to the world … to win souls unto Christ.”[7]

I understood even at that early age that sharing the gospel was based on a great love for all our Heavenly Father’s children.

As General Authorities assigned to work on Preach My Gospel 15 years ago, we concluded that the attribute of love was essential to missionary work in our day, just as it has always been. Chapter 6, on Christlike attributes, including charity and love, has consistently been the most popular chapter among missionaries.

As emissaries of the Savior, most missionaries feel this kind of love, and when they do, their efforts are blessed. When members gain a vision of this kind of love, which is essential in assisting the Lord in His purpose, the Lord’s work will be accomplished.

I was privileged to have a small role in a marvelous example of this kind of love. When I was serving as President of the Pacific Islands Area, I received a call from President R. Wayne Shute. As a young man, he served a mission in Samoa. Later, he returned to Samoa as a mission president.[8] When he telephoned me, he was the Apia Samoa Temple president. One of his young missionaries, when he was mission president, was Elder O. Vincent Haleck, who is now the Area President in the Pacific. President Shute had great love and respect for Vince and the entire Haleck family. Most of the family were members of the Church, but Vince’s father, Otto Haleck, the patriarch of the family (of German and Samoan descent), was not a member. President Shute knew I was attending a stake conference and other meetings in American Samoa, and he asked me if I would consider staying in Otto Haleck’s residence with the view of sharing the gospel with him.

My wife, Mary, and I stayed with Otto and his wife, Dorothy, in their beautiful home. At breakfast I shared a gospel message and invited Otto to meet with the missionaries. He was kind, but firm, in refusing my invitation. He said he was pleased that many members of his family were Latter-day Saints. But he forcefully indicated that some of his Samoan mother’s ancestors had been early Christian ministers in Samoa, and he felt a great allegiance to their traditional Christian faith.[9] Nevertheless, we left as good friends.

Later, when President Gordon B. Hinckley was preparing to dedicate the Suva Fiji Temple, he had his personal secretary, Brother Don H. Staheli,[10] call me in New Zealand to make arrangements. President Hinckley wanted to fly from Fiji to American Samoa to meet the Saints. A certain hotel used in a previous visit was suggested. I asked if I could make different arrangements. Brother Staheli said, “You are the Area President; that would be fine.”

I immediately called President Shute and told him that perhaps we had a second chance at spiritually blessing our friend Otto Haleck. This time the missionary would be President Gordon B. Hinckley. I asked if he thought it would be appropriate for the Halecks to host all of us in President Hinckley’s travel group.[11] President and Sister Hinckley, their daughter Jane, and Elder and Sister Jeffrey R. Holland were also part of the travel group. President Shute, working with the family, made all the arrangements.[12]

When we arrived from Fiji after the temple dedication, we were warmly greeted.[13] We spoke that evening to thousands of Samoan members and then proceeded to the Haleck family compound. When we gathered for breakfast the next morning, President Hinckley and Otto Haleck had already become good friends. It was interesting to me that they were having much the same conversation I had had with Otto more than a year earlier. When Otto expressed his admiration for our Church but reaffirmed his commitment to his existing church, President Hinckley put his hand on Otto’s shoulder and said, “Otto, that’s not good enough; you ought to be a member of the Church. This is the Lord’s Church.” You figuratively could see the resistive armor fall away from Otto with an openness to what President Hinckley said.

This was the beginning of additional missionary teaching and a spiritual humility that allowed Otto Haleck to be baptized and confirmed a little over a year later. One year after that, the Haleck family was sealed as an eternal family in the temple.[14]

What touched my heart throughout this incredible experience was the overwhelming ministering love exhibited by President Wayne Shute for his former missionary, Elder Vince Haleck, and his desire to see the entire Haleck family united as an eternal family.[15]

When it comes to gathering Israel, we need to align our hearts with this kind of love and move away from feelings of mere responsibility[16] or guilt to feelings of love and participation in the divine partnership of sharing the Savior’s message, ministry, and mission with the world.[17]

As members we can show our love for the Savior and our brothers and sisters throughout the world by making simple invitations. The new Sunday meeting schedule represents an exceptional opportunity for members to successfully and lovingly invite friends and associates to come and see and feel a Church experience.[18] A spiritual sacrament meeting, hopefully as sacred as what Elder Jeffrey R. Holland described yesterday, will be followed by a 50-minute meeting focused on the New Testament and the Savior or relevant conference addresses also focused on the Savior and His doctrine.

Some Relief Society sisters have wondered why they have been given a “gathering” assignment along with priesthood quorum members. There are reasons for this, and President Nelson set forth many of them in the last general conference. He concluded, “We simply cannot gather Israel without you.”[19] In our day we are blessed that approximately 30 percent of our full-time missionaries are sisters. This provides additional incentive for Relief Society sisters to lovingly share the gospel. What is needed is a loving, compassionate, spiritual commitment by each of us—men, women, youth, and children—to share the gospel of Jesus Christ. If we show love, kindness, and humility, many will accept our invitation. Those who choose not to accept our invitation will still be our friends.

Love is also at the center of our temple and family history effort to gather Israel on the other side of the veil. When we learn of the trials and hardships our ancestors faced, our love and appreciation for them is magnified. Our temple and family history effort has been strengthened to a significant degree by the new adjustments in both the Sunday meeting schedule and the youth advancement in classes and quorums. These changes provide for earlier and more powerful attention to learning about our ancestors and gathering Israel on the other side of the veil. Both temple and family history work are greatly enhanced.

The internet is a powerful tool; the home is now our primary family history center. Our young members are exceptionally skilled in family history research and are spiritually motivated to perform baptisms for their ancestors, whom they have learned to love and appreciate. Since the change allowing many 11-year-olds to perform baptisms for the dead, temple presidents across the world report greatly increased attendance. One temple president informs us that “there has been a remarkable increase in baptismal patrons … and the addition of 11-year-olds brings more families. … Even at their [young] age, they appear to sense reverence and purpose for the ordinance they are performing. It is beautiful to watch!”[20]

I know our Primary and youth leaders are making and will continue to make family history and temple work a major effort. Relief Society sisters and priesthood brethren can lovingly help fulfill their temple and family history responsibility individually and also by assisting and inspiring children and youth to gather Israel on the other side of the veil. This is particularly important in the home and on the Sabbath. I promise that lovingly performing ordinances for ancestors will strengthen and protect our youth and families in a world that is becoming increasingly evil. I also personally testify that President Russell M. Nelson has received profoundly important revelations relating to temples and temple work.

The new emphasis on home-centered gospel study and living and the resources that are provided by the Church are a great opportunity for lovingly preparing eternal families and individuals to meet and live with God.[21]

When a man and woman are sealed in the temple, they enter the holy order of matrimony in the new and everlasting covenant, an order of the priesthood.[22] Together they obtain and receive priesthood blessings and power to direct the affairs of their family. Women and men have unique roles as outlined in “The Family: A Proclamation to the World,”[23] but their stewardships are equal in value and importance.[24] They have equal power to receive revelation for their family. When they work together in love and righteousness, their decisions are heaven blessed.

Those who seek to know the will of the Lord as individuals and for their families must strive for righteousness, meekness, kindness, and love. Humility and love are the hallmark of those who seek the Lord’s will, especially for their families.

Perfecting ourselves, qualifying ourselves for the blessings of covenants, and preparing to meet God are individual responsibilities. We need to be self-reliant and anxiously engaged in making our homes a refuge from the storms that surround us[25] and “a sanctuary of faith.”[26] Parents have a responsibility to lovingly teach their children. Homes filled with love are a joy, a delight, and a literal heaven on earth.[27]

My mother’s favorite hymn was “Love at Home.”[28] Whenever she heard the first phrase, “There is beauty all around when there’s love at home,” she became visibly touched and teary. As children we were aware that we lived in that kind of home; it was one of her highest priorities.[29]

In addition to encouraging a loving atmosphere in the home, President Nelson has focused on limiting media use that disrupts our primary purposes.[30] One adjustment that will benefit almost any family is to make the internet, social media, and television a servant instead of a distraction or, even worse, a master. The war for the souls of all, but particularly children, is often in the home. As parents we need to make sure that media content is wholesome, age appropriate, and consistent with the loving atmosphere we are trying to create.

Teaching in our homes needs to be clear and compelling[31] but also spiritual, joyful, and full of love.

I promise that as we focus on our love for the Savior and His Atonement, make Him the centerpiece of our efforts to gather Israel on both sides of the veil, minister to others, and individually prepare to meet God, the influence of the adversary will be diminished and the joy, delight, and peace of the gospel will magnify our homes with Christlike love.[32] I testify of these doctrinal promises and bear a sure witness of Jesus Christ and His atoning sacrifice in our behalf, in the name of Jesus Christ, amen.

Doctrine and Covenants 4:1, 5. ↩

Moroni 7:47. ↩

See “Charity and Love,” Preach My Gospel: A Guide to Missionary Service, rev. ed. (2019), 124. ↩

See Deuteronomy 6:5; Matthew 22:36–40. ↩

See “Responsibilities of Elders Quorum and Relief Society Presidencies in Member Missionary and Temple and Family History Work,” notice, Oct. 6, 2018. ↩

My grandfather was authorized to give a patriarchal blessing to grandchildren who lived in different stakes. Mine was given to me at age 11 because he was ill and it was thought that he might pass away. ↩

Patriarchal blessing given to Quentin L. Cook by patriarch Crozier Kimball, Oct. 13, 1951, Draper, Utah. ↩

President R. Wayne Shute also served with his wife Lorna on other various kinds of missions in Shanghai, China; Armenia; Singapore; and Greece. After Lorna passed, he married Rhea Mae Rosvall, and they served in the Australia Brisbane Mission. Seven of his nine children have served full-time missions. During two of the years he was serving as a mission president in Samoa, Elder John H. Groberg was serving as mission president in Tonga. The experiences both of them had are legendary. ↩

Otto Haleck was a lay leader in the Congregational Christian Church of Samoa, which had roots stemming from the London Missionary Society. His father was of German heritage from Dessau, Germany. ↩

President Don H. Staheli is currently serving as the president of the Bountiful Utah Temple. ↩

President Gordon B. and Sister Marjorie P. Hinckley and their daughter Jane Hinckley Dudley, Elder Jeffrey R. and Sister Patricia T. Holland, Elder Quentin L. and Sister Mary G. Cook, and Brother Don H. Staheli were all present. ↩

Elder O. Vincent Haleck informs me that his father invited Vince and his brother David to return from overseas to inspect the house and be there for President Hinckley’s visit. Elder Haleck said his father declared, “These could be angels, you know.” He told his sons if they were going to host the prophet, they would want the house to be perfect. ↩

President Hinckley was greeted by the national leadership of American Samoa and many thousands of Samoans at the football stadium. ↩

Uniting families through diligent missionary work has been a great characteristic of both the Samoan and other Polynesian peoples. ↩

President Shute was so loved and appreciated that he was invited to speak at Otto Haleck’s funeral service in 2006. ↩

“Sometimes we may initially serve from a sense of duty or obligation, but even that service can lead us to draw on something higher … to serve in ‘a more excellent way’ [1 Corinthians 12:31]” (Joy D. Jones, “For Him,” Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 50). ↩

See Tad R. Callister, The Infinite Atonement (2000), 5–8. ↩

Church members should coordinate with the missionaries whenever they are making invitations. ↩

Russell M. Nelson, “Sisters’ Participation in the Gathering of Israel,” Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 70. ↩

Report by President B. Jackson and Sister Rosemary M. Wixom, president and matron of the Salt Lake Temple, to the Primary General Presidency, Mar. 2019. The Wixoms noted that they “are ordering more XXXS baptism clothing to meet the demand!” ↩

See Russell M. Nelson, “Opening Remarks,” Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 6–8. ↩

See Doctrine and Covenants 131:1–4. ↩

See “The Family: A Proclamation to the World,” Ensign or Liahona, May 2017, 145. ↩

“Every father is to his family a patriarch and every mother a matriarch as coequals in their distinctive parental roles” (James E. Faust, “The Prophetic Voice,” Ensign, May 1996, 6). ↩

See Doctrine and Covenants 45:26–27; 88:91. ↩

Russell M. Nelson, “Becoming Exemplary Latter-day Saints,” Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 113. ↩

See “Home Can Be a Heaven on Earth,” Hymns, no. 298. ↩

“Love at Home,” Hymns, no. 294. ↩

If this kind of love is to be achieved, the direction in Doctrine and Covenants 121:41–42 should be the goal: ↩

See Russell M. Nelson, “Sisters’ Participation in the Gathering of Israel,” 69; see also Russell M. Nelson, “Hope of Israel” (worldwide youth devotional, June 3, 2018), HopeofIsrael.ChurchofJesusChrist.org. ↩

In a sense, the home is like a one-room school for children of all ages. When teaching the 11-year-old, we can’t ignore the 3-year-old. ↩

See John 17:3; 2 Nephi 31:20; Moroni 7:47. ↩

Elder D. Todd Christofferson
Preparing for the Lord’s Return

In two weeks, we will celebrate Easter. The Resurrection confirms the divinity of Jesus Christ and the reality of God the Father. Our thoughts turn to the Savior, and we ponder “His matchless life and the infinite virtue of His great atoning sacrifice.”[1] I hope we also think about His pending return when “He will rule as King of Kings and … Lord of Lords.”[2]

Some time ago in Buenos Aires, Argentina, I participated in a conference with leaders from a wide variety of religious faiths. Their love for their fellowman was unmistakable. They were intent on relieving suffering and helping people rise above oppression and poverty. I reflected on the numerous humanitarian undertakings of this Church, including projects in collaboration with a number of the faith groups represented in the conference. I felt deep gratitude for the generosity of the members of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints that makes such Christlike service possible.

In that moment, the Holy Spirit affirmed two things to me. First, the work of ministering to temporal needs is vital and must continue. The second was unexpected, yet powerful and clear. It was this: beyond selfless service, it is supremely important to prepare the world for the Second Coming of the Lord Jesus Christ.

When He comes, oppression and injustice will not only diminish; they will cease:

“The wolf also shall dwell with the lamb, and the leopard shall lie down with the kid, and the calf and the young lion and fatling together; and a little child shall lead them. …

“They shall not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain, for the earth shall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the sea.”[3]

Poverty and suffering will not only decline; they will vanish:

“They shall hunger no more, neither thirst any more; neither shall the sun light on them, nor any heat.

“For the Lamb which is in the midst of the throne shall feed them, and shall lead them unto living fountains of waters: and God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes.”[4]

Even the pain and sorrow of death will be done away:

“In that day an infant shall not die until he is old; and his life shall be as the age of a tree;

“And when he dies he shall not sleep, that is to say in the earth, but shall be changed in the twinkling of an eye, and shall be caught up, and his rest shall be glorious.”[5]

So yes, let us do all we can to relieve suffering and sorrow now, and let us devote ourselves more diligently to the preparations needed for the day when pain and evil are ended altogether, when “Christ [shall] reign personally upon the earth; and … the earth will be renewed and receive its paradisiacal glory.”[6] It will be a day of redemption and judgment. The former Anglican Bishop of Durham, Dr. N. T. Wright, has aptly described the significance of Christ’s Atonement, Resurrection, and Judgment in overcoming injustice and putting all things right.

He said: “God has fixed a day on which he will have the world judged rightly by a man whom he has appointed—and of this he has given assurance to all by raising this man from the dead. The facts about Jesus of Nazareth, and especially about his resurrection from the dead, are the foundation of the assurance that the world is not random. It is not ultimately a chaos; that when we do justice in the present we are not whistling in the dark, trying to shore up a building that will ultimately collapse, or to fix a car which is actually bound for the scrap-heap. When God raised Jesus from the dead, that was the microcosmic event in which the ultimate macrocosmic act of judgment was contained in a nutshell, [the] seed … of the ultimate hope. God declared, in the most powerful way imaginable, that Jesus of Nazareth really was the Messiah. … In the greatest irony of history, [Jesus] himself underwent cruel and unjust judgment, coming to the place which symbolized and drew together all the myriad cruelties and injustices of history, to bear that chaos, that darkness, that cruelty, that injustice, in himself, and to exhaust its power.”[7]

While I was at the conference in Buenos Aires that I mentioned earlier, the Spirit made clear to me that The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is uniquely empowered and commissioned to accomplish the necessary preparations for the Lord’s Second Coming; indeed, it was restored for that purpose. Can you find anywhere else a people who embrace the present era as the prophesied “dispensation of the fulness of times,” in which God has purposed to “gather together in one all things in Christ”?[8] If you don’t find here a community intent on accomplishing what needs to be accomplished for both the living and the dead to prepare for that day, if you don’t find here an organization willing to commit vast amounts of time and funds to the gathering and preparation of a covenant people ready to receive the Lord, you won’t find it anywhere.

Speaking to the Church in 1831, the Lord declared:

“The keys of the kingdom of God are committed unto man on the earth, and from thence shall the gospel roll forth unto the ends of the earth. …

“Call upon the Lord, that his kingdom may go forth upon the earth, that the inhabitants thereof may receive it, and be prepared for the days to come, in the which the Son of Man shall come down in heaven, clothed in the brightness of his glory, to meet the kingdom of God which is set up on the earth.”[9]

What can we do to prepare now for that day? We can prepare ourselves as a people; we can gather the Lord’s covenant people; and we can help redeem the promise of salvation “made to the fathers,” our ancestors.[10] All of this must occur in some substantial measure before the Lord comes again.

First, and crucial for the Lord’s return, is the presence on the earth of a people prepared to receive Him at His coming. He has stated that those who remain upon the earth in that day, “from the least [to] the greatest, … shall be filled with the knowledge of the Lord, and shall see eye to eye, and shall lift up their voice, and with the voice together sing this new song, saying: The Lord hath brought again Zion. … The Lord hath gathered all things in one. The Lord hath brought down Zion from above. The Lord hath brought up Zion from beneath.”[11]

In ancient times, God took the righteous city of Zion to Himself.[12] By contrast, in the last days a new Zion will receive the Lord at His return.[13] Zion is the pure in heart, a people of one heart and one mind, dwelling in righteousness with no poor among them.[14] The Prophet Joseph Smith stated, “We ought to have the building up of Zion as our greatest object.”[15] We build up Zion in our homes, wards, branches, and stakes through unity, godliness, and charity.[16]

We must acknowledge that the building up of Zion occurs in tumultuous times—“a day of wrath, a day of burning, a day of desolation, of weeping, of mourning, and of lamentation; and as a whirlwind it shall come upon all the face of the earth, saith the Lord.”[17] Thus, the gathering into stakes becomes “for a defense, and for a refuge from the storm, and from wrath when it shall be poured out without mixture upon the whole earth.”[18]

Just as in former times, we “meet together oft, to fast and to pray, and to speak one with another concerning the welfare of [our] souls. And … to partake of bread and [water], in remembrance of the Lord Jesus.”[19] As President Russell M. Nelson explained in general conference last October, “The long-standing objective of the Church is to assist all members to increase their faith in our Lord Jesus Christ and in His Atonement, to assist them in making and keeping their covenants with God, and to strengthen and seal their families.”[20] Accordingly, he emphasizes the significance of temple covenants, hallowing the Sabbath, and a daily feasting upon the gospel, centered at home and supported by an integrated study curriculum at church. We want to know about the Lord, and we want to know the Lord.[21]

An underlying effort in building Zion is the gathering of the Lord’s long-dispersed covenant people.[22] “We believe in the literal gathering of Israel and in the restoration of the Ten Tribes.”[23] All who will repent, believe on Christ, and be baptized are His covenant people.[24] The Lord Himself prophesied that before His return, the gospel would be preached in all the world[25] “to recover [His] people, which are of the house of Israel,”[26] “and then shall the end come.”[27] Jeremiah’s prophecy is being fulfilled:

“Therefore, behold, the days come, saith the Lord, that [they] shall no more [say], The Lord liveth, that brought up the children of Israel out of the land of Egypt;

“But, The Lord liveth, that brought up the children of Israel from the land of the north, and from all the lands whither he had driven them: and I will bring them again into their land that I gave unto their fathers.”[28]

President Nelson has repeatedly emphasized that the “gathering [of Israel] is the most important thing taking place on earth today. Nothing else compares in magnitude, nothing else compares in importance, nothing else compares in majesty. And if you choose to, … you can be a big part of it.”[29] The Latter-day Saints have always been a missionary people. Hundreds of thousands have responded to mission calls since the beginning of the Restoration; tens of thousands currently serve. And, as Elder Quentin L. Cook has just taught, all of us can participate in simple and natural ways, in love, inviting others to join us at church, visit in our homes, become part of our circle. Publication of the Book of Mormon was the signal that the gathering had begun.[30] The Book of Mormon itself is the instrument of gathering and conversion.

Also vital to the preparation for the Second Coming is the great redemptive effort on behalf of our ancestors. The Lord promised to send Elijah the prophet before the Second Coming, “the great and dreadful day of the Lord,”[31] to “reveal … the Priesthood” and “plant in the hearts of the children the promises made to the fathers.”[32] Elijah did come as promised. The date was April 3, 1836; the place was the Kirtland Temple. In that place and in that moment, he did indeed confer the promised priesthood, the keys for the redemption of the dead and the union of husbands, wives, and families across all generations of time and throughout all eternity.[33] Without this, the purpose of creation would be frustrated, and in that sense, the earth would be cursed or “utterly wasted.”[34]

At the youth devotional preceding the dedication of the Rome Italy Temple, the hundreds of young men and women in attendance displayed to President Nelson the cards they had prepared with names of their ancestors. They were ready to enter the temple to perform vicarious baptisms for those ancestors as soon as it opened. It was a supremely gratifying moment, yet but one example of the accelerating effort to establish Zion for the generations that have gone before.

While we strive to be diligent in building up Zion, including our part in the gathering of the Lord’s elect and the redemption of the dead, we should pause to remember that it is the Lord’s work and He is doing it. He is the Lord of the vineyard, and we are His servants. He bids us labor in the vineyard with our might this “last time,” and He labors with us.[35] It would probably be more accurate to say He permits us to labor with Him. As Paul said, “I have planted, Apollos watered; but God gave the increase.”[36] It is He who is hastening His work in its time.[37] Employing our admittedly imperfect efforts—our “small means”—the Lord brings about great things.[38]

This great and last dispensation is building steadily to its climax—Zion on earth being joined with Zion from above at the Savior’s glorious return. The Church of Jesus Christ is commissioned to prepare—and is preparing—the world for that day. And so, this Easter, let us truly celebrate the Resurrection of Jesus Christ and all that it portends: His return to reign for a thousand years of peace, a righteous judgment and perfect justice for all, the immortality of all who ever lived upon this earth, and the promise of eternal life. Christ’s Resurrection is the ultimate assurance that all will be put right. Let us be about building up Zion to hasten that day. In the name of Jesus Christ, amen.

“The Living Christ: The Testimony of the Apostles,” Ensign or Liahona, May 2017, inside front cover. ↩

“The Living Christ.” ↩

2 Nephi 21:6, 9; see also Isaiah 11:6, 9. ↩

Revelation 7:16–17. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 101:30–31. ↩

Articles of Faith 1:10. ↩

N. T. Wright, “Full of the Knowledge of the Lord” (sermon given at matins, Durham, England, Mar. 30, 2016), ntwrightpage.com. ↩

Ephesians 1:10. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 65:2, 5. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 2:2. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 84:98–100. ↩

The scriptural record states simply, “It came to pass that Zion was not, for God received it up into his own bosom” (Moses 7:69). ↩

God declared: “And righteousness will I send down out of heaven; and truth will I send forth out of the earth, to bear testimony of mine Only Begotten; his resurrection from the dead; yea, and also the resurrection of all men; and righteousness and truth will I cause to sweep the earth as with a flood, to gather out mine elect from the four quarters of the earth, unto a place which I shall prepare, an Holy City, that my people may gird up their loins, and be looking forth for the time of my coming; for there shall be my tabernacle, and it shall be called Zion, a New Jerusalem. … And for the space of a thousand years the earth shall rest” (Moses 7:62, 64). ↩

See Doctrine and Covenants 97:21; Moses 7:18. ↩

Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Joseph Smith (2007), 186. ↩

See D. Todd Christofferson, “Come to Zion,” Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2008, 37–40. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 112:24. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 115:6. ↩

Moroni 6:5–6; see also Alma 6:5–6; 4 Nephi 1:12. ↩

Russell M. Nelson, “Opening Remarks,” Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 7. ↩

See Jeremiah 31:34; John 17:3; Doctrine and Covenants 84:98. ↩

One by one, the elect are gathered into the stakes of Zion, “the places of [God’s] appointment” (Doctrine and Covenants 109:39; see also Doctrine and Covenants 124:36). ↩

Articles of Faith 1:10. ↩

See 2 Nephi 30:2. ↩

See Joseph Smith—Matthew 1:31. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 39:11. ↩

Joseph Smith—Matthew 1:31. ↩

Jeremiah 16:14–15; see also Jeremiah 23:7–8. ↩

Russell M. Nelson, “Hope of Israel” (worldwide youth devotional, June 3, 2018), HopeofIsrael.ChurchofJesusChrist.org; see also Russell M. Nelson, “Remnants Gathered, Covenants Fulfilled,” in Paul Y. Hoskisson, ed., Sperry Symposium Classics: The Old Testament (2005), 1–17. ↩

See 3 Nephi 21:1–7. ↩

Malachi 4:5. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 2:1–2. ↩

See Doctrine and Covenants 110. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 2:3; see also Malachi 4:6. ↩

See Jacob 5:71–72. ↩

1 Corinthians 3:6. ↩

See Doctrine and Covenants 88:73. ↩

See 1 Nephi 16:29. ↩

Elder Gerrit W. Gong
Good Shepherd, Lamb of God

Dear brothers and sisters, have you ever had trouble falling asleep and tried counting imaginary sheep? As fluffy sheep jump over a fence, you count: 1, 2, 3, … 245, 246, … 657, 658 …[1]

In my case, counting sheep doesn’t make me sleepy. I worry about missing or losing one, and that keeps me awake.

With the shepherd boy who became a king, we declare:

“The Lord is my shepherd; I shall not want.

“He maketh me to lie down in green pastures: he leadeth me beside the still waters.

“He restoreth my soul.”[2]

At this Easter season, we celebrate the Good Shepherd, who is also the Lamb of God. Of all His divine titles, no others are more tender or telling. We learn much from our Savior’s references to Himself as the Good Shepherd and from prophetic testimonies of Him as the Lamb of God. These roles and symbols are powerfully complementary—who better to succor each precious lamb than the Good Shepherd, and who better to be our Good Shepherd than the Lamb of God?

“For God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son,” and God’s Only Begotten Son laid down His life in willing obedience to His Father.[3] Jesus testifies, “I am the good shepherd: the good shepherd giveth his life for the sheep.”[4] Jesus had power to lay down His life and power to take it up again.[5] United with His Father, our Savior uniquely blesses us, both as our Good Shepherd and as the Lamb of God.

As our Good Shepherd, Jesus Christ calls us in His voice and His name. He seeks and gathers us. He teaches us how to minister in love. Let us consider these three themes, beginning with Him calling us in His voice and His name.

First, our Good Shepherd “calleth his own sheep by name. … They know his voice.”[6] And “in his own name he doth call you, which is the name of Christ.”[7] As we seek with real intent to follow Jesus Christ, inspiration comes to do good, to love God, and to serve Him.[8] As we study, ponder, and pray; as we regularly renew sacramental and temple covenants; and as we invite all to come to His gospel and ordinances, we are hearkening to His voice.

In our day, President Russell M. Nelson counsels us to call the restored Church by the name Jesus Christ revealed: The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.[9] The Lord said, “Whatsoever ye shall do, ye shall do it in my name; therefore ye shall call the church in my name; and ye shall call upon the Father in my name that he will bless the church for my sake.”[10] Across the world, in our hearts and homes, we call upon the Father in the name of Jesus Christ. We are grateful for such generous blessing of our home-centered, Church-supported worship, gospel study, and wholesome family activities.

Second, our Good Shepherd seeks and gathers us into His one fold. He asks, “What man of you, having an hundred sheep, if he lose one of them, doth not leave the ninety and nine in the wilderness, and go after that which is lost, until he find it?”[11]

Our Savior reaches out to the one and to the ninety-and-nine, often at the same time. As we minister, we acknowledge the ninety-and-nine who are steadfast and immovable, even while we yearn after the one who has strayed. Our Lord seeks and delivers us “out of all places,”[12] “from the four quarters of the earth.”[13] He gathers us by holy covenant and His atoning blood.[14]

Our Savior told His New Testament disciples, “Other sheep I have, which are not of this fold.”[15] In the Americas, the resurrected Lord testified to Lehi’s covenant children, “Ye are my sheep.”[16] And Jesus said yet other sheep would hear His voice.[17] What a blessing the Book of Mormon is as another testament witnessing the voice of Jesus Christ!

Jesus Christ invites the Church to receive all who hear His voice[18] and keep His commandments. The doctrine of Christ includes baptism by water and by fire and the Holy Ghost.[19] Nephi asks, “If the Lamb of God, he being holy, should have need to be baptized by water, to fulfil all righteousness, O then, how much more need have we, being unholy, to be baptized, yea, even by water!”[20]

Today our Savior desires that what we do and who we are becoming will invite others to come, follow Him. Come find love, healing, connection, and covenant belonging in Him, including in God’s holy temple, where sacred ordinances of salvation can bless all family members, thus gathering Israel on both sides of the veil.[21]

Third, as the “Shepherd of Israel,”[22] Jesus Christ exemplifies how shepherds in Israel minister in love. When our Lord asks if we love Him, as He did with Simon Peter, our Savior implores: “Feed my lambs. … Feed my sheep. … Feed my sheep.”[23] The Lord promises that when His shepherds feed His lambs and sheep, those in His fold “shall fear no more, nor be dismayed, neither shall they be lacking.”[24]

Our Good Shepherd cautions that shepherds in Israel must not slumber,[25] nor scatter or cause the sheep to go astray,[26] nor look our own way for our own gain.[27] God’s shepherds are to strengthen, heal, bind up that which is broken, bring again that which was driven away, seek that which was lost.[28]

The Lord also warns of hirelings, who “careth not for the sheep,”[29] and “false prophets, who come to you in sheep’s clothing, but inwardly they are ravening wolves.”[30]

Our Good Shepherd rejoices when we exercise individual moral agency with intention and faith. Those in His fold look to our Savior in gratitude for His atoning sacrifice. We covenant to follow Him, not passively, blindly, or “sheepishly,” but instead desiring with all our hearts and minds to love God and our neighbor, bearing one another’s burdens and rejoicing in one another’s joys. As Christ freely dedicated His will to the will of the Father, so we reverently take upon us His name. We gladly seek to join His work of gathering and ministering to all of God’s children.

Brothers and sisters, Jesus Christ is our perfect Good Shepherd. Because He has laid down His life for us and is now gloriously resurrected, Jesus Christ is also the perfect Lamb of God.[31]

The sacrificial Lamb of God was foreshadowed from the beginning. The angel told Adam his sacrifice “is a similitude of the sacrifice of the Only Begotten of the Father,” which invites us to “repent and call upon God in the name of the Son forevermore.”[32]

Father Abraham, who established covenant blessings for all the nations of the earth, experienced what it meant to offer his begotten son.

“And Isaac spake unto Abraham his father, and said, My father: and he said, Here am I, my son. And he said, Behold the fire and the wood: but where is the lamb … ?

“And Abraham said, My son, God will provide himself a lamb.”[33]

Apostles and prophets foresaw and rejoiced in the foreordained mission of the Lamb of God. John in the Old World and Nephi in the New World testified of “the Lamb of God,”[34] “yea, even the Son of the Eternal Father[,] … the Redeemer of the world.”[35]

Abinadi testified of Jesus Christ’s atoning sacrifice: “All we, like sheep, have gone astray; we have turned every one to his own way; and the Lord hath laid on him the [iniquity] of us all.”[36] Alma called the great and last sacrifice of the Son of God the “one thing which is of more importance than they all.” Alma encouraged, “Have faith on the Lamb of God”; “come and fear not.”[37]

A dear friend shared how she gained her precious testimony of the Atonement of Jesus Christ. She grew up believing sin always brought great punishment, borne by us alone. She pleaded to God to understand the possibility of divine forgiveness. She prayed to understand and know how Jesus Christ can forgive those who repent, how mercy can satisfy justice.

One day her prayer was answered in a spiritually transforming experience. A desperate young man came running out of a grocery store carrying two bags of stolen food. He ran into a busy street, chased by the store manager, who caught him and began yelling and fighting. Instead of feeling judgment for the frightened young man as a thief, my friend was unexpectedly filled with great compassion for him. Without fear or concern for her own safety, she walked straight up to the two quarreling men. She found herself saying, “I will pay for the food. Please let him go. Please let me pay for the food.”

Prompted by the Holy Ghost and filled with a love she had never felt before, my friend said, “All I wanted to do was to help and save the young man.” My friend said she began to understand Jesus Christ and His Atonement—how and why with pure and perfect love Jesus Christ would willingly sacrifice to be her Savior and Redeemer, and why she wanted Him to be.[38]

No wonder we sing:

See, the Good Shepherd is seeking,

Seeking the lambs that are lost,

Bringing them in with rejoicing,

Saved at such infinite cost.[39]

As Lamb of God, our Savior knows when we feel alone, diminished, uncertain, or afraid. In vision, Nephi saw the power of the Lamb of God “[descend] upon the saints of the church of the Lamb, and upon the covenant people of the Lord.” Though “scattered upon all the face of the earth … they were armed with righteousness and with the power of God in great glory.”[40]

This promise of hope and comfort includes our day.

Are you the only member of the Church in your family, school, workplace, or community? Does your branch sometimes feel small or isolated? Have you moved to a new place, perhaps with an unfamiliar language or customs? Perhaps your life’s circumstances have changed, and things you never thought possible now confront you? Our Savior assures us, whatever our circumstances, whoever we are, in the words of Isaiah: “He shall gather the lambs with his arm, and carry them in his bosom, and shall gently lead those that are with young.”[41]

Brothers and sisters, our Good Shepherd calls us in His voice and in His name. He seeks, gathers, and comes to His people. Through His living prophet and each of us, He invites all to find peace, purpose, healing, and joy in the fulness of His restored gospel and on His covenant path. By example, He teaches the shepherds of Israel to minister in His love.

As Lamb of God, Jesus’s divine mission was foreordained and rejoiced in by apostles and prophets. His Atonement, infinite and eternal, is central to the plan of happiness and the purpose of creation. He assures us that He carries us next to His heart.

Dear brothers and sisters, may we desire to be “humble followers of God and the Lamb,”[42] perhaps someday to have our names written in the Lamb’s book of life,[43] to sing the song of the Lamb,[44] to be invited to the supper of the Lamb.[45]

As Shepherd and Lamb, He calls, Come again “to the true knowledge … of [your] Redeemer, … [your] great and true shepherd.”[46] He promises that “by his grace [we] may [become] perfect in Christ.”[47]

At this Easter season, we praise Him:

“Worthy is the Lamb!”[48]

“Hosanna to God and the Lamb!”[49]

I testify of Him, our perfect Good Shepherd, the perfect Lamb of God. He calls us by our name, in His name—even the sacred and holy name of Jesus Christ—amen.

A popular song suggests: ↩

Psalm 23:1–3. ↩

John 3:16. ↩

John 10:11. ↩

See John 10:15, 17–18. ↩

John 10:3–4. ↩

Alma 5:38; see also Alma 5:37, 39, 59–60. ↩

See Moroni 7:13; Doctrine and Covenants 8:2–3. ↩

See Russell M. Nelson, “The Correct Name of the Church,” Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2018, 87–89. ↩

3 Nephi 27:7; emphasis added. ↩

Luke 15:4, emphasis added; see also Doctrine and Covenants 18:15. ↩

Ezekiel 34:12; see also Jeremiah 31:10; Ezekiel 34:6, 11–14; Micah 5:8; Matthew 10:6; 15:24. These prophecies of scattering and the prophecies and promises of covenant gathering are a consistent theme of the prophets, including President Russell M. Nelson. ↩

1 Nephi 22:25. ↩

See Hebrews 13:20. ↩

John 10:16; see also 3 Nephi 15:21; 16:1, 3; Doctrine and Covenants 10:59–60. ↩

3 Nephi 15:24; see also 3 Nephi 15:17, 21. ↩

See 3 Nephi 16:1, 3; see also Doctrine and Covenants 10:59–60. ↩

See Mosiah 26:21. ↩

See 2 Nephi 31:13–14, 21. ↩

2 Nephi 31:5; see also Alma 7:14. ↩

See Malachi 4:5–6; John 15:9–13; Mosiah 25:18; Helaman 11:21; see also Russell M. Nelson, “Hope of Israel” (worldwide youth devotional, June 3, 2018), HopeofIsrael.ChurchofJesusChrist.org; Russell M. Nelson, “The Gathering of Scattered Israel,” Ensign or Liahona, Nov. 2006, 79–82. ↩

Psalm 80:1. ↩

John 21:15–17; see also the entire chapter. ↩

Jeremiah 23:4. ↩

See Nahum 3:18. ↩

See Jeremiah 23:1; 50:6, 44. ↩

See Isaiah 56:11; Ezekiel 34:2–6. ↩

See Ezekiel 34:2–6. ↩

John 10:13. ↩

3 Nephi 14:15; see also Matthew 7:15; Alma 5:60. ↩

See 2 Nephi 9:10–12. By conquering physical death and spiritual separation, the Lamb of God makes possible the gathering of all so there is, in time and eternity, one Shepherd. ↩

Moses 5:7–8. ↩

Genesis 22:7–8; see also Jacob 4:5. ↩

John 1:29; 1 Nephi 11:21. ↩

1 Nephi 11:21, 27. ↩

Mosiah 14:6; see also Isaiah 53:6. ↩

Alma 7:7, 14–15. ↩

Conversation with Pornthip “Tippy” Coyle, Feb. 2019, used with permission. ↩

“Dear to the Heart of the Shepherd,” Hymns, no. 221. Other hymns that highlight our Shepherd and His sheep include the following: “The Lord My Pasture Will Prepare,” Hymns, no. 109: ↩

1 Nephi 14:14; see also 1 Nephi 13:35, 37: “Plain and precious [writings shall] … come forth … by the gift and power of the Lamb. … If [we] endure unto the end … [we] shall be saved in the everlasting kingdom of the Lamb.” ↩

Isaiah 40:11. ↩

Helaman 6:5. ↩

See Revelation 21:27. ↩

See Revelation 15:3; Doctrine and Covenants 133:56. ↩

See Revelation 19:9; Doctrine and Covenants 58:11; see also Revelation 7:17: “For the Lamb … shall feed them, and shall lead them unto living fountains of waters: and God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes”; Revelation 22:1: The “pure river of water of life, clear as crystal, proceeding out of the throne of God and of the Lamb.” ↩

Helaman 15:13. ↩

See Moroni 10:32–33. ↩

Revelation 5:12. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 109:79. ↩

Elder Ronald A. Rasband
Build a Fortress of Spirituality and Protection

My dear brothers and sisters, as this conference comes to a close, I give thanks to our Father in Heaven for the counsel, truths, and revelation shared at this pulpit during the past two days. We have been taught by servants of God called to speak His holy words. The Lord has reminded us in latter-day revelation, “Whether by mine own voice or … the voice of my servants, it is the same.”[1]

Looking over this vast congregation of Saints and picturing members watching general conference all over the world, I think of the gathering in the Book of Mormon when Jesus Christ appeared to the Nephites following His Crucifixion. He taught them the gospel and then encouraged, “Go ye unto your homes, and ponder upon the things which I have said, and ask of the Father, in my name, that ye may understand.”[2]

“Go ye unto your homes, and ponder” is the next step in taking to heart the words of prophets and Church leaders spoken in this sacred setting. Christ-centered homes are fortresses for the kingdom of God on earth in a day when, as prophesied, the devil “rage[s] in the hearts of the children of men, and stir[s] them up to anger against that which is good.”[3]

People have built fortresses throughout history to keep the enemy outside. Often those fortresses included a guard tower where watchmen—like prophets—warned of menacing forces and coming attacks.

In early Utah pioneer times, my great-grandfather Thomas Rasband and his family were some of the first settlers to enter the Heber Valley in the beautiful Wasatch Mountains of Utah.

In 1859, Thomas helped construct the Heber fort, built for their protection. It was a simple structure of cottonwood logs positioned one next to the other, forming the perimeter of the fort. Log cabins were built inside the fortress using that common wall. The structure provided both security and safety for those pioneer families as they put down roots and worshipped the Lord.

So it is with us. Our homes are fortresses against the evils of the world. In our homes we come unto Christ by learning to follow His commandments, by studying the scriptures and praying together, and by helping one another stay on the covenant path. The new emphasis on personal and family study in the home through the curriculum Come, Follow Me is designed “to deepen our conversion and help us become more like Jesus Christ.”[4] In so doing we will become what Paul called “new creature[s]”[5] with our hearts and souls in tune with God. We need that strength to face and deflect the assaults of the adversary.

As we live with devotion born of faith in Jesus Christ, we will feel the peaceful presence of the Holy Ghost, who guides us to truth, inspires us to live worthy of the Lord’s blessings, and bears witness that God lives and loves us. All this within the fortress of our own homes. But remember, our homes are only as powerful as the spiritual strength of each one of us within the walls.

President Russell M. Nelson has taught, “In coming days, it will not be possible to survive spiritually without the guiding, directing, comforting, and constant influence of the Holy Ghost.”[6] As the Lord’s living prophet, seer, and revelator in this day, the watchman on the tower of our fortress, The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, he sees the advances of the enemy.

Brothers and sisters, we are at war with Satan for the souls of men. The battle lines were drawn in our pre-earth life. Satan and a third of our Father in Heaven’s children turned away from His promises of exaltation. Since that time, the adversary’s minions have been fighting the faithful who choose the Father’s plan.

Satan knows his days are numbered and that time is growing shorter. As crafty and cunning as he is, he will not win. However, his battle for each one of our souls rages on.

For our safety, we must build a fortress of spirituality and protection for our very souls, a fortress that will not be penetrated by the evil one.

Satan is a subtle snake, sneaking into our minds and hearts when we have let our guard down, faced a disappointment, or lost hope. He entices us with flattery, a promise of ease, comfort, or a temporary high when we are low. He justifies pride, unkindness, dishonesty, discontent, and immorality, and in time we can be “past feeling.”[7] The Spirit can leave us. “And thus the devil cheateth their souls, and leadeth them away carefully down to hell.”[8]

In contrast, we often feel the Spirit so powerfully as we sing praises to God with words like these:

A mighty fortress is our God,

A tower of strength ne’er failing.

A helper mighty is our God,

O’er ills of life prevailing.[9]

When we build a fortress of spiritual strength, we can shun the advances of the adversary, turn our backs on him, and feel the peace of the Spirit. We can follow the example of our Lord and Savior, who, when tempted in the wilderness, said, “Get thee behind me, Satan.”[10] We each have to learn by the experiences of life how to do that.

Such righteous purpose is well described in the Book of Mormon when Captain Moroni prepared the Nephites to face attacks from a deceitful, bloodthirsty, power-hungry Amalickiah. Moroni constructed fortresses to protect the Nephites “that they might live unto the Lord their God, and that they might maintain that which was called by their enemies the cause of Christians.”[11] Moroni “was firm in the faith of Christ”[12] and was faithful “in keeping the commandments of God … and resisting iniquity.”[13]

When the Lamanites came to battle, they were astonished by the Nephites’ preparation, and they were defeated. The Nephites thanked “the Lord their God, because of his matchless power in delivering them from the hands of their enemies.”[14] They had built fortresses for protection on the outside, and they had built faith in the Lord Jesus Christ on the inside—deep in their souls.

What are some ways we can fortify ourselves in troubled times, that we may be “instruments in the hands of God to bring about this great work”?[15] Let’s look to the scriptures.

We are obedient. The Lord commanded Father Lehi to send his sons back to Jerusalem to “seek the records, and bring them down hither into the wilderness.”[16] Lehi didn’t question; he didn’t wonder why or how. Nor did Nephi, who responded, “I will go and do the things which the Lord hath commanded.”[17]

Do we act with the willing obedience of Nephi? Or are we more inclined to question God’s commands as did Nephi’s brothers, whose lack of faith eventually turned them away from the Lord? Obedience, exercised with “holiness of heart,”[18] is what the Lord asks of us.

We trust the Lord, who said to Joshua as he prepared to lead the Israelites into the promised land, “Be strong and of … good courage; be not afraid, neither be thou dismayed: for the Lord thy God is with thee whithersoever thou goest.”[19] Joshua trusted those words and counseled the people, “Sanctify yourselves: for to morrow the Lord will do wonders among you.”[20] The Lord parted the waters of the Jordan, and the Israelites’ 40 years of wandering in the wilderness ended.

We stand for the truth, as did the prophet Abinadi in the Book of Mormon. Arrested, brought before King Noah and his wicked priests, Abinadi taught the Ten Commandments and preached powerfully that Christ would “come down among the children of men, and … redeem his people.”[21] He then, with faith deep within him, proclaimed, “O God, receive my soul,”[22] and Abinadi “suffered death by fire.”[23]

We make and renew our covenants by partaking of the sacrament and by worshipping in the temple. The sacrament is the centerpiece of our Sunday worship, where we are receiving the promise to “always have his Spirit to be with [us].”[24] With that sacred ordinance we commit to take upon us the name of Jesus Christ, to follow Him, and to shoulder our responsibilities in this divine work as He did. In the temple we can “lay aside the things of this world”[25] and feel the Lord’s presence and His transcendent peace. We can focus on our ancestors, our families, and eternal life in the presence of the Father. No wonder President Nelson stated recently in Rome, “The good that will emanate from this temple is incalculably great.”[26]

We should have integrity in all that we do. We should develop discernment and discipline so that we do not have to continually determine what is right and what is wrong. We should take to heart the words of Peter, the early Church Apostle, who cautioned, “Be sober, be vigilant; because your adversary the devil, as a roaring lion, walketh about, seeking whom he may devour.”[27]

As we diligently strengthen our fortifications, we become like Jesus Christ, as His true disciples, with our very souls in His protection.

Your testimony of Jesus Christ is your personal fortress, the security for your soul. When my great-grandfather and his fellow pioneers built the Heber fort, they put up one log at a time until the fort was “fitly framed together”[28] and they were protected. So it is with testimony. One by one we gain a witness from the Holy Spirit as He speaks to our own spirit, teaching “truth in the inward parts.”[29] When we live the gospel of Jesus Christ, when we draw upon the Savior’s Atonement and press forward with faith, not fear, we are fortified against the wiles of the adversary. Our testimonies connect us to the heavens, and we are blessed with “the truth of all things.”[30] And, like pioneers protected by a fortress, we are safely encircled in the arms of the Savior’s love.

The prophet Ether taught, “Wherefore, whoso believeth in God might with surety hope for a better world, yea, even a place at the right hand of God, which hope cometh of faith, maketh an anchor to the souls of men, which would make them sure and steadfast, always abounding in good works, being led to glorify God.”[31]

My dear brothers and sisters, I leave you with my blessing to go forth with confidence in the Lord and in His gospel. Put your arms around those who stumble and, with the strength of the Spirit within you, lead them lovingly back to the fortress of spirituality and protection. Seek “to be like Jesus”[32] in all that you do; shun evil and temptations; repent, as we were admonished yesterday by our dear prophet; be honest in heart; be upright and pure; show compassion and charity; and love the Lord your God with the devotion of a true disciple.

Our testimonies of the gospel of Jesus Christ, our homes, our families, and our membership in The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints will be our personal fortresses of protection surrounding us and shielding us from the power of the evil one. Of this I bear my solemn witness in the name of our Lord and Savior, even Jesus Christ, amen.

Doctrine and Covenants 1:38. ↩

3 Nephi 17:3. ↩

2 Nephi 28:20. ↩

Come, Follow Me—For Individuals and Families: New Testament 2019, v. ↩

2 Corinthians 5:17. ↩

Russell M. Nelson, “Revelation for the Church, Revelation for Our Lives,” Ensign or Liahona, May 2018, 96. ↩

1 Nephi 17:45. ↩

2 Nephi 28:21. ↩

“A Mighty Fortress Is Our God,” Hymns, no. 68. ↩

Luke 4:8. ↩

Alma 48:10. ↩

Alma 48:13. ↩

Alma 48:16. ↩

Alma 49:28. ↩

Alma 26:3. ↩

1 Nephi 3:4. ↩

1 Nephi 3:7. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 46:7. ↩

Joshua 1:9. ↩

Joshua 3:5. ↩

Mosiah 15:1. ↩

Mosiah 17:19. ↩

Mosiah 17:20. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 20:77. ↩

Doctrine and Covenants 25:10. ↩

Russell M. Nelson, in Tad Walch, “President Nelson Refers to Apostles Peter, Paul during Rome Temple Dedication,” Deseret News, Mar. 10, 2019, deseretnews.com. ↩

1 Peter 5:8. ↩

Ephesians 2:21. ↩

Psalm 51:6. ↩

Moroni 10:5. ↩

Ether 12:4. ↩

“I’m Trying to Be like Jesus,” Children’s Songbook, 78. ↩